OK, let's get started.
As a recap of some of the stuff
that we've talked about so far,
we've formulated this
reinforcement learning problem
where we have
states and actions.
We have some trajectories
that we might be collecting,
which are sequences
of states and actions.
We have a reward
function, which tells
us how good is a particular
state and action,
and also a policy,
which is usually
what we're trying to learn.
And this is representing
the behavior
that we're trying to learn.
And then the goal of
reinforcement learning,
which we talked about
in the first lecture,
is to try to maximize the
expected sum of rewards.
So we want to produce behavior
that leads to positive outcomes.
And we can actually
mathematically write this
down as an expectation over
the probability distribution
over trajectories, where this
probability distribution is
a function of the
policy which is acting
in the world, the
environment dynamics which
might be stochastic, and of
course, the reward function.
Last week on Friday, we
started talking about one way
to do this, which is if you
have expert demonstrations,
you could try to
imitate the expert
by trying to maximize the
likelihood of the actions
that the demonstrator did--
so trying to actually produce
a policy that leads to
actions that the expert would
have taken.
This is a very simple
and scalable approach,
but it cannot outperform the
demonstrator and doesn't allow
improvement through
trial and error.
We also introduced the notion
of an offline algorithm that
only uses an existing
data set, and no new data
from a learned policy, and
an online algorithm that
uses new data from
the learned policy.
And today we'll be
talking about ways
in which we can
use reinforcement
learning to outperform
the demonstrator
to improve from practice.
And specifically,
we'll be starting
to talk about online
reinforcement learning
algorithms.
Particularly, our first
online RL algorithm
will be policy gradients.
We'll talk about a couple of
different variants of policy
gradients and introduce both the
mathematical derivation for it,
as well as some of the
intuition behind it.
And policy gradients
are the basis
for some popular reinforcement
learning algorithms, including
ones that are used to train
legged robots, algorithms that
are used to train
language models,
and are also part of
the default project.
We won't get the
complete algorithm
that was used to train these
today, but we'll get most of--
or halfway there, basically.
And by Friday, we'll have
most of the algorithm for it.
And then the key
goals will be to try
to get the intuition
behind policy gradients,
how to implement them,
and when to use them.
OK.
So the outline of an online
reinforcement learning algorithm
is going to look
something like this.
So first, we need to initialize
our policy in some way.
When you train a
neural network, you
need to initialize its weights.
We could initialize the
weights of our policy randomly.
We could also initialize
it with imitation learning.
We could also use heuristics.
It depends on the
problem setting.
And after we
initialize our policy,
we'll run our policy
to collect some data.
So actually, try out
different things in the world.
Then we'll use that batch of
data to improve the policy.
And then we will
repeat that process.
We'll then collect new data
with our updated policy
and update our policy again
using that latest batch of data.
So we're going to attempt the
task and try to get better.
So what this might look
like is the first iteration,
we attempt whatever--
some kind of simple
2D navigation task.
The reward for some
of them is bad.
The reward for other
trajectories is OK.
And then after more
iterations of this,
we might have a policy
that's a bit better that
is able to get a higher
reward but isn't perfect.
So sometimes it gets
a higher reward,
sometimes it still
gets a low reward.
Then we'll use that to
improve the policy again.
And after more
iterations, hopefully, we
will get a policy that
is able to succeed.
So this is this notion of
online reinforcement learning
where we're collecting
data online and improving
using that data.
So we talked about
this reinforcement
learning objective.
And say you have
some policy, and you
want to actually understand
how good that policy is,
to do that, we can't
just actually look
at the weights of
the neural network.
We actually have
to run the policy
to understand how good it is.
And so what we'll do is to
estimate this expectation, which
is a function of the policy.
We can actually just run
the policy multiple times,
observe the resulting reward,
and then compute the average
over the observed reward.
And that's an estimate of
how good our policy is.
So we can then sum over the
samples from our policy.
Now, let's start to think about
how we actually-- so we have
this trial and error process.
We collect some data and
we improve our policy.
Collecting the data
is straightforward.
We've talked about
how to run a policy
to get a rollout
in the environment.
We can sample an action,
observe the next state,
then run that through our policy
again to get a new action,
and repeat that process.
But how do we actually
then improve our policy
after we've collected that data?
So we have our objective, and
this can be written down--
we have some policy pi-theta.
And our goal is to maximize
the expected rewards when
we sample from that policy.
So we can consider the
trajectories that are sampled
from the policy as being drawn
by some distribution that
I'll write as p-theta of tau--
theta because the
distribution over trajectories
is a function of the
policy that you're using.
And our goal is to maximize
the sum of rewards.
I'm going to use shorthand here.
And I'm going to use shorthand
for r of the trajectory, where
this just means the sum of the
rewards along that trajectory.
So our goal is to
maximize the rewards.
We're going to maximize
this with respect
to our policy parameters theta.
Now, how do we
actually optimize this?
So we want to use gradient
descent because we typically
train neural networks
with gradient descent.
We need to figure out the
gradient of this objective
with regard to theta.
And we'll refer to this
term right here as j-theta
to be able to write it.
This is the objective that
we're trying to maximize.
And it's a little
bit challenging
to try to get a
gradient of this thing
directly because
the relationship
that this has on theta is
through the trajectories
that we sampled.
So we can't just differentiate
through the sampling process.
And that sampling
process also depends
on the dynamics of the world,
which we also don't know.
So if we're going to
think about trying
to get a gradient
of j-theta, it's
helpful to write down this
expectation as an integral.
So this expectation
can be written
as an integral of p-theta
of tau times r of tau d tau.
So this is just from the
definition of an expectation.
Now, because an
integral is a summation,
and that's a linear
operation, we
can bring the gradient
inside the integral.
And so in particular,
what that looks
like is the integral of
the gradient of p-theta
of tau r of tau.
Now, this doesn't really
help us directly in any way,
because we don't want to have to
evaluate this integral in order
to take a gradient.
And at this point, there is kind
of a trick, a convenient trick
that we can use
to try to put this
into a form that's more useful.
And in particular,
the trick is that--
we'll write it over here--
is that if you
think about p-theta
of tau times the gradient of
p-theta of tau-- actually,
sorry, times the
gradient of the log.
Does anyone remember what
the gradient of a log is
or the derivative of log?
[INAUDIBLE]
1 over, right?
Then what this is equal to?
This is equal to p-theta of tau
times 1 over p-theta of tau.
And then we need to
use the chain rule
to apply the gradient to this.
And so with the
chain rule, we'll
get the gradient
of p-theta of tau.
And these two will
then cancel out.
And this is equal to the
gradient of p-theta of tau.
And the reason why this is a
convenient equality between
gradient of p-theta--
and this is we
could actually then
replace the gradient of p-theta
down here with this first thing
right here.
If we replace this gradient
of p-theta of tau right here,
we replace this, we now get an
integral of p-theta of tau times
grad log p-theta of tau
times r of tau d tau.
Now, this is something
that's useful
because we can
now represent this
as an expectation, this
first term right here.
And so this is equal
to an expectation
of tau sampled from
p-theta of tau of grad log
p-theta of tau times r of tau.
So what we did there is
we used this log trick
to then get the p-theta out here
and then get an expectation.
And we're starting to get to
something that's actually more
what we can evaluate.
And in particular,
this expectation
is something that we can
estimate with samples.
And now theta is actually
appearing on the inside here.
And that means that
this is actually
getting closer to something
that we can evaluate.
We still have this
term right here,
which doesn't look
like pi of a given S.
So we need to work on this term.
But we're starting to
get towards something
that we can evaluate.
So the question is, how is this
more useful than the first term,
because we still
have the sampling,
and the issue with
the first case
was that we can't differentiate
through the sampling?
Now, the thing
that's different here
is that theta actually appears
inside the expectation.
Now we're not going to
be able to differentiate
through the sampling, still.
But the thing that's
useful here is
that we will actually
be able to differentiate
with respect to theta.
And we're still not going to
differentiate in this part,
but we'll be able to get an
estimate that's still useful.
And we could potentially
draw many, many samples.
And then measure this
quantity to get actually
a pretty accurate representation
of the gradient in a way that
actually depends on theta.
OK.
Let's talk a little bit
about this term right here.
And actually, maybe in
case it's useful in terms
of where we're at so far, we can
show that on the slides as well.
So we looked at this j of theta,
wrote it down as an integral.
We found this convenient
identity over here,
where p grad log p
is equal to grad p.
And then we can use that to
derive this second equation
right here.
And now we're right here.
So for this part,
for grad log p,
this is something
that we can write out.
And if we use--
if we remember that p-theta
of tau equals p of S1 times pi
of at given St and P of
St plus 1, given St at,
and then with a product over t.
Then when we take the log
of this, it's over there,
the log of p-theta of
tau is equal to the log
of p of S1 plus the sum over T
of the log of pi plus the log
of the dynamics.
And then once we actually take
the gradient of log p tau, then
the gradient of this
with respect to theta,
theta doesn't affect the
initial state distribution.
It also doesn't affect
the dynamics in any way.
And so the gradient
of log p-theta of tau
is equal to just the gradient
of this term right here.
So the gradient of log
pi-theta of a given S.
And so this is really
useful because this
means that we can actually
plug in this over there.
And this is actually something
that we can evaluate.
We can evaluate
the gradient of--
or the log-- the
gradient of log pi.
And this is just
taking a backward pass
through the log of the
output of our neural network.
And so then we actually get a
gradient that we can evaluate.
So the gradient that we
get when we plug things in,
the gradient of j-theta
when we plug this in,
is we have an expectation
over trajectories
sampled from our policy.
And inside that expectation,
we can bring the gradient
inside that summation.
And so we'll have a sum
over time steps of grad log
pi of at given St, right here.
And then we still
have our r of t
right here, so we can
write that as r of tau.
We could also write it as a
summation of r of St comma at.
So this is what's called the
policy gradient or the vanilla
policy gradient.
And this is a lot
nicer than the version
up there because we can sample
trajectories from our policy,
compute their reward.
Also, compute the
gradient of each of log
of pi for each of the actions.
And then sum those
together, multiply,
and we can get a
gradient that we
can apply to the weights
of our neural network.
That's actually leading
to a higher reward.
So again, on the
slides, we wrote down
what the probability
of a trajectory is.
If you take the log
of that, you get
a summation instead
of a product,
and the log of each of
the individual terms.
Then if we plug that
into our gradient
and we take the
gradient of log p tau,
then the first term
and the last term
go away because they
don't depend on theta.
And then we get this final
term when we plug it in.
So this is the gradient.
When we run policy gradient,
we'll collect data.
And then we'll
evaluate this equation.
And then we'll use that
to represent the gradient
of the weights of the policy.
And then run gradient descent,
apply that to our policy,
and then repeat the process.
So yeah, we also talked
about this verbally.
But in order to estimate
this gradient here,
we'll run the policy
to collect some data.
We'll then improve the
policy using that data.
In particular, you can
think of the first summation
as collecting n samples
for that expectation.
And ideally, n is larger
because the higher n
is, the better an
estimate you're
going to get of the
expectation of the integral.
And then once we
evaluate this gradient
that we're estimating
with samples,
we'll then take a gradient
step on our policy parameters.
And so the full
algorithm looks something
like sampling trajectories
from our policy,
evaluating an estimate of the
gradient using those samples,
applying that to the weights,
and then repeating this process
to collect a new batch of
data, recomputing the gradient,
and improving the policy.
So the question is,
what does it look
like to use the data to
estimate this gradient term--
the first term or
the second term?
The first term.
Yeah.
So when we're using the data to
compute this first term, what
we're doing is we're getting
a bunch of states and actions,
a bunch of trajectories.
We're getting n trajectories
at each-- in this case,
have length t time steps.
And we'll be taking
the states and actions
in those trajectories,
passing the state
through the policy
as a forward pass
to get the probability
of our actions.
We'll then evaluate the action
in the data, the probability
of that action in the data under
the distribution, the policy
output.
So it's like a
categorical distribution.
We'll then get the probability.
We'll take the log
of that probability.
And then we take the
gradient right here,
which will just be
a forward pass--
sorry, a backward pass
through the network
after taking the log of the
policy output for that action.
So this is called the REINFORCE
algorithm or the vanilla policy
gradient algorithm.
So this came out.
This is just r of tau.
So I'm using r of tau
as shorthand for this,
just because I didn't want to
write the summation five times.
But yeah, this is
exactly r of tau.
Yeah, exactly.
So this is an estimate
because we're only
going to be taking n samples
to estimate this expectation.
If you took infinite,
then this would be exact.
Of course, taking infinite
samples is not possible.
The gradient.
Yeah.
So the gradient right
here, this is going
to depend on the architecture.
The question was, do we
compute this by hand?
You can use automatic
differentiation.
So whatever library,
PyTorch or whatever,
that can compute
that for you, so you
don't have to write it out.
Great.
So let's talk about some of
the intuition behind this.
So there's the math.
But what does this
gradient actually mean?
So if you look at
this, maybe let's
start by looking
at the first term.
The first term if we think
back to imitation learning,
this first term is actually
the same as the gradient
of the imitation
learning objective.
So in imitation
learning, we were
trying to mimic actions from
some demonstration data set
by maximizing the
log probability
or minimizing the
negative log probability.
And if you take the
gradient of that,
it's similarly going to be the
gradient of the log probability.
So you can think about
this first term as saying,
I'm going to basically
try to increase
the likelihood of the
actions in the online data.
But then for the
second term, it's
weighting that by the
reward of that trajectory.
How good was that trajectory?
And so you can think about
this as the imitation gradient,
but weighted by the sum of
rewards seen in the data.
And so essentially,
you're going to increase
the likelihood of actions
that had high reward
and decrease the
likelihood of actions
that were taken in negative
reward trajectories.
And so you're
actually going to be
imitating your own
data, the data that
was collected by the policy.
But depending on whether it's
high reward or low reward,
you actually might have
a negative gradient.
If it's negative
reward, that's actually
going to push you away
from the bad stuff
and push you towards
the good stuff.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
So this is inside
the first summation.
You can see the eye
comes up right here.
So we're summing a
bunch of directories,
and then, yeah, this is all
within the summation over n.
So the question is,
is the difference
between this and
imitation learning where
imitation learning you're
either right or wrong,
or here you're like,
this amount of right
or this amount of wrong?
So you can apply this--
well, in principle, you
can apply this in scenarios
where the reward is very sparse.
And so you can actually
apply it in scenarios
where the reward is just 1 if
you succeeded, and 0 otherwise.
Now, this algorithm may not do
very well in those scenarios,
and we'll talk about that.
One of the key differences
with imitation learning
is that you're actually doing
this on your own rollouts.
Actually, the policy is
collecting its own data
and then applying this
objective to its own data.
And so that's one
of the differences.
And then second
is we're actually
using this reward, whereas
in imitation learning,
you're just blindly imitating
all the data without any notion
of how good the data is.
And it assumes that
it's good data.
Yeah.
How do you sample the first
state of the trajectory?
This is something
that's typically
defined by the problem setting.
So in some problem
settings, if you're
trying to train an agent to
play pinball or something,
then the initial state will just
be given by the pinball machine.
In other cases, in
language modeling,
the initial state or observation
might be the first question
that the user asked.
So it's usually thought of as
a property of the environment.
So the question is,
can you use this
to improve imitation
learning by weighting
the trajectories by reward?
Yeah, you could
definitely do that.
We will also talk about some of
the good things and bad things
about this objective
in the coming slides.
So the question
was, in practice,
does it make sense to start
with imitation learning,
run that for some
number of iterations,
and then switch to this?
That can definitely make sense.
If you start completely from
a randomly initialized policy,
it will do random stuff.
And if you have a very dense
reward signal, that can be OK.
But in other scenarios, if you
have access to demonstrations,
then initializing it
with demonstrations
can be a very good
fit, and then it
will allow you to improve on
top of your initial policy.
So the question is, if you don't
have a good conception of what's
good and bad, what the
reward function should be,
can you use imitation
learning to get
an initial sense for that?
We'll talk about reward
learning in a few lectures
and how you can potentially
use expert data for that.
In practice, it's challenging.
So we talked about how
this intuitively increasing
likelihood on high
reward trajectories
and decreasing likelihood on
negative reward trajectories.
If we actually look
at this visually,
say that we took a
few trajectories--
one of them had good reward,
one of them had bad reward--
and this red is showing
our initial distribution
over trajectories, what
this gradient is going to do
is it's going to increase the
likelihood on the green part.
So you'll get something
that looks like this.
And then it'll decrease the
likelihood on the red part,
so you'll get something
that looks like this.
And it'll encourage
the policy to take
actions that are more like
the high-reward trajectory.
[INAUDIBLE]
In even more brief terms,
you can think of this
as trying to do more of the good
stuff and less of the bad stuff
that you observe.
And then you can
also think about this
as a formalization
of trial and error,
where you're actually going
to try to do different things.
And if you see good
stuff happening,
then you'll try to
do more of that.
And if you make a mistake, then
you'll try to stop doing that.
Cool.
So now I have a
question for you.
So let's look at an example.
Say that we're trying
to have a humanoid
learn how to walk in
simulation, and we'll
define the reward function
to be the forward velocity
of the robot.
This means that the reward
function will be positive
if it's moving forward.
It may also be negative if
the robot is moving backwards.
It might be 0 if the
robot is not moving.
First, we'll sample
from our policy.
Say we have a policy that's
not very good at the beginning.
So in the first trajectory,
maybe it falls backwards.
In the second
trajectory, maybe it
falls forward, which will
actually technically give it
positive reward.
So the sum of rewards
will be positive.
Maybe another trajectory,
it manages to stand still.
So the rewards
would be 0 for that.
In another trajectory, maybe
it takes one small step forward
and then falls backwards.
And so the initial reward at
the beginning of the trajectory
would actually be
getting positive rewards.
And then later on, it would
be getting negative rewards,
and the sum of rewards
would be negative.
And then maybe the
last trajectory
is it takes one
large step backwards,
and then a small step forwards.
And in this case, it would
have negative rewards, and then
some positive rewards,
but the sum of rewards
would still be negative.
Now my question for you is,
what will the gradient that we
defined here, what will
it encourage the policy
to do if this is your data
set, if these are the five
trajectories that you sampled?
This is going to be one
of our simpler examples,
and then we'll move to
more complex examples
in a couple more slides.
So I'd encourage you to
pair up for a minute,
discuss it briefly,
and then we'll
come back and share
in 1 or 2 minutes.
OK, let's come back.
If you want to share your
answer, can you raise your hand?
OK.
So the gradient
will encourage it
to fall forwards and
potentially stand still.
Cool.
That's mostly correct.
So if we think through
each of these trajectories,
the first one, the reward
will be negative here.
It will also be negative.
The sum of rewards over
the entire trajectory
will be negative
for 1, 4, and 5.
It should be about 0 for
3, and for 2, the sum
should be positive.
And so what this means is
you'll get negative gradients
for any actions that were
taken in 1, 4, and 5.
You'll get positive gradients
for all the actions taken in 2.
And you'll get roughly 0
gradients for all the actions
that are taken in trajectory 3.
And so this means that it will
encourage it to fall forwards.
And it'll encourage it
to not do the things that
were in 1, 4, and 5.
So it will discourage
it from taking steps
backwards or forwards and
will also discourage it
from falling backwards.
Cool.
So yeah.
So we encourage the policy
to fall forwards and not
take steps.
This is distressing because
we don't want our policy
to fall forward.
We want to take steps.
And so this is
kind of an example
of how the gradient that we're
getting is noisy, high variance.
It means that depending on
what these trajectories are,
the gradient might
vary drastically.
So if you do actually have
some trajectories that
are walking forwards,
you might actually
get a very different
gradient estimate
from this set of trajectories.
And so that's the definition
of having noise or having
high variance.
So the question is, why are we
getting multiple trajectories
from the same policy?
Why not just get one?
There's two reasons for this.
One is that the policy
is not deterministic.
And so if we want to explore
different strategies,
we will get different samples
of different strategies
because it's non-deterministic.
And the second reason
is also the environment
might be stochastic.
And so even if you have
a deterministic policy,
you might see
different outcomes,
and this will help you learn
about those different outcomes.
There's one thing that we can do
about this that we can already
directly improve the gradient
in a fairly simple way.
And in particular, one
observation that we might make
is that if you're in the
middle of a trajectory
and you take an
action, that action
has no influence
on previous states.
And right now, the gradient
that is using the rewards at all
states in the trajectory--
in the gradient
update, and it's even
telling us to take actions
later in the trajectory
if the reward earlier in the
trajectory was good or bad.
And so one of the
things that we can do
is if one of our
trajectories was
to take a large step backwards
and then a small step forwards,
then we should actually be able
to learn from this trajectory
that taking a small
step forward is good.
And the way that we can do
that is instead of having this
be a sum from t equals 1 to
T, what we can instead do
is we can actually have
this summation start at t.
And so we can have
this essentially be--
let's use a different letter.
So we'll have t prime
that is starting at t
and going to capital T. And
now this is reward of St prime,
at prime.
And by having it only
look at future rewards,
this means that we're now
incorporating the fact
that current actions can
only affect the future,
and not affect the past.
[INAUDIBLE]
Oh, yes.
Sorry.
One other thing that
you have to do here--
yes, good point-- is to
actually move this summation
inside this summation here.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
Why can we do this?
So the reason is that we
know that our action at--
let's say our action
at time equals 100.
So let's say if t equals 100,
so we're looking at a100.
We know that this 100 is only
going to influence rewards
in the future.
And this isn't going to have any
impact on states in the past.
So this is going to be
completely independent of St50--
or sorry, S50.
So this doesn't affect
S50 or S51 or S99.
And this means that the--
yeah, because of
that independence,
we can then drop the rewards.
We can drop that from
the equation and--
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
And only look at--
when looking at increasing the
likelihood of an action at time
t, only use the future
rewards in that influence.
It's a little bit hard to
write out mathematically
why you can do that.
I can maybe think
about whether there's
a nice mathematical
expression for that,
but it's really just about
causality in the world.
And so basically, policy
behavior at time t
is not going to influence
rewards at earlier time steps.
Cool.
I think that this equation--
OK.
I don't have the typo in
this equation, so, yeah.
We're bringing this summation
inside the other one.
And it's only going to be a
factor of the future time steps.
And this means that for
this example right here,
we will be decreasing
the likelihood of actions
at the beginning
of the trajectory.
And then the future summations
will become positive
because you took a step forward.
Then you'll actually start to
be increasing the likelihood
of taking a small step forward.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
So a very good
point is this still
doesn't help if you
take a step forward
and then you take
a step backwards.
And the reason why it doesn't--
the reason why that's actually
a little bit difficult to handle
is that it's possible that
the step forwards actually
cause you to fall
backwards, or cause
you to take a step backwards.
A big part of
reinforcement learning
is thinking about what influence
does actions have on the future.
And you need to learn
that from experience.
And if you take a step forward,
it means that it could--
from the algorithm's
point of view,
actually, have caused something
bad to happen in the future,
and so we can't
drop those rewards.
So the question was,
if you say that you
had a lot of really bad
stuff at the beginning
and then you took a good action
later on in the trajectory,
would you have enough
time to accumulate that?
So in your particular
example, you started getting--
capital T was equal to 10,
and you started seeing--
you did something really
good at time step 6.
Now, at time step 6, what
this will look like is
you'll have grad
log a6 given S6.
And then you'll have a summation
from t prime equals 6 to 10
of our St prime, at prime.
And so if you did get a high
reward from that action,
immediately or in the
next four time steps,
then you would actually increase
the likelihood on that action.
Now, it's really going to depend
a lot on the reward function.
So you're saying that for
fixed horizon problems,
you're actually going
to be giving it--
the gradient will be different
if you're summing over 10
rewards versus over 4 rewards.
So one of the things
that's important
if you have a fixed
time horizon T is
for this to be a proper state--
and actually to be
truly Markovian-- you
need it to contain information
about the future dynamics.
And if it's fixed
at 10 and the policy
doesn't know if the
horizon is about to finish,
then it's actually not
a truly Markovian state.
You need to actually give it
information about how many time
steps it has left to
succeed, and then you
can incorporate
that into the state.
And so you would actually
have different states
in those different
circumstances.
OK.
So now another example for you.
And this actually comes
back to the question
that came up earlier,
although it's actually
slightly different.
So say that the robot--
we now have a
version that is only
depending on future rewards.
We have the same
version of the problem,
but now our policy is
a little bit better.
One of the trajectories
falls forward.
slowly stumbles forward.
One of the trajectories
steadily walks forward.
And one of the
trajectories runs forward.
My question for you is, what
will the gradient encourage
the policy to do in this case?
And we can use this version,
the updated version.
And so I'll encourage you to
pair up again and discuss this,
and then we'll come
back in 2 minutes.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
OK.
Let's come back.
Please raise your hand if you
want to share your answer.
OK?
Yeah.
So the first answer
was that it's
going to get the highest reward
for the stuff that is moving
forward at higher velocity.
So it's going to encourage
it to do that, the highest
velocity stuff the most.
And you're saying
that even if it
makes any sort of
forward progress,
it will still encourage
it to do that.
So another hypothesis
was that if you go back
to the previous example,
it might encourage
it to fall forward and then
get back up again and then
fall forward and get
back up again, especially
if it's easy to fall forward.
Now, getting up
again is actually
a little bit more challenging,
so that might also
be a little tricky.
And so the thoughts there
was that the fourth one,
if the reward is--
it might dominate if that
one has a much higher reward
than the others.
If they're more even in terms
of velocity and it's just move
forward, then it won't
necessarily dominate,
and you'll do all four.
So all of the rewards in these
cases will all be positive.
I think what a lot of
people were getting at
is that the reward of this
last one will be the highest,
and so we'll be
encouraged to do this.
But because all of
these 1, 2, and 3
also have positive
rewards, the policy
is actually also
still going to be
encouraged to do those things.
So basically, when this term is
nonnegative, when it's positive,
you're still going to be
increasing the likelihood
on the actions in
these trajectories.
Now it won't do it as
frequently as running forward,
but it will still be
encouraged to do that.
And that might be a
little bit concerning
because some of the
time, it will actually
be encouraging it
to stumble forward.
And ideally, we would
actually, in this case,
want a policy that can
actually have the policy run
as fast as possible.
So the question was, is this
because of local minimum?
It seems like with
this reward function,
the best outcome
is to run forward,
and so why are we getting
this kind of objective?
The reason for this is
because the gradient is noisy.
It comes down to variance.
And if you do have a
policy that runs forward,
it will encourage it to
keep on running forward.
But when you have
other data in there,
that other data will
influence it in some ways.
And so it won't necessarily
converge to a local optimum,
because at this point,
it will encourage
it to run forward more.
And then the next batch of
data will run forward more,
and it'll encourage it
to run forward even more.
So eventually, it will
converge to the global optimum,
but it will get there more
slowly because the gradient has
a lot of variance, depending
on the samples that you select.
Will this encourage the
robot to roll forward?
With this data, it
will not encourage
it to roll forward unless some
weird combination of gradients
causes that.
But yeah, generally,
it will not.
If you had data of
rolling forward,
then it would encourage
it to roll forward.
So the question
is, can the agent
learn from a subset
of characters instead
of the whole trajectory?
In this case, it will
learn from all future steps
in the trajectory.
So that is a subset,
but it might not be--
and I guess-- in
the next lecture,
we'll talk about more
sophisticated ways to estimate
this--
are smarter basically.
Cool.
So the thing that we
saw here is that things
are sensitive to the scaling
of the reward function.
And on the flip side, if
everything was negative--
it came up in the
question before--
we would actually only be
getting negative gradients
to our policy and no
actual positive gradients.
And that's actually
a big problem
with this kind of approach
is that it depends
on the scale of the reward.
And there's actually
a very simple thing
that we can do to fix this.
And so in particular,
what we can do
is when we are using
this gradient, which is
the expectation of p of tau--
I'll maybe do the first version
just to make it a bit shorter,
but we get the gradient of
log p of tau times r of tau.
And what we can do is instead
of having this be r of tau,
we can actually
subtract a constant,
where that constant could be
equal to the average reward.
And if we subtract the
average reward from this,
this means that things that
are better than average
will increase the
likelihood, and things
that are below
average will actually
lead us to decrease likelihood.
So this will be negative.
Now, you might be wondering,
can we just add this b here?
Did I just make that up?
Why can we do that?
Why are we allowed to do that?
We can see what the effect
that this has on the gradient.
And what we can show
is we can actually
show that if you subtract
a constant in expectation,
this has zero effect
on the gradient.
And in particular-- so
this is the gradient of J.
And if we look at what effect
this has on the gradient
and expectation, we can look
at essentially the expectation
of grad log p times b.
And it's possible to show
that this in expectation
is actually equal to zero.
And in particular, if we write
this out as the gradient of--
or sorry, the expectation
is the integral
of p of tau times grad
log p of tau times bd tau.
We can then use the
same trick that we
used before, but in reverse.
This is equal to the integral
of grad p-theta of tau times bd
tau.
I'm a little bit out of
space, but the gradient
can be moved to the
outside of the integral
because this is a
linear operation.
We can also move b
outside the integral
because it's a constant.
And so this is equal
to the gradient
b times the gradient of the
integral of p-theta of tau d
tau.
Now this integral is just equal
to 1, and the gradient of 1
is 0.
So this is 1, this is
0, and b times 0 is 0.
And so this means that
the expectation, this
is going to have 0
effect on the gradient.
And so just to maybe write that
out a little bit more cleanly,
the expectation of the
gradient of log p times
b-- so basically, the
fact that this baseline
is having on this gradient.
We can write that
as the integral.
We can then use the
log trick in reverse.
We can move b and the gradient
outside of the integral.
This integral is equal to
1, the gradient of 1 is 0,
and then we get 0.
So this means that we
can add this baseline.
So the reason why this
constant term-- the question
was this constant term wouldn't
be helpful if we could actually
truly evaluate the expectation.
And yeah, that's correct.
So if we had this expectation
and could measure this exactly,
then we wouldn't need this.
The reason why this is
helpful is because we
have this expectation.
Basically, you can think
of it as reducing--
it's a way to reduce the
variance of your estimate
of this expectation, and it's
an unbiased way to do that.
So in particular, as long as
the baseline is a constant,
then it won't
change the behavior
of the gradient in expectation.
This means that it's unbiased.
This is a term from statistics,
talking about effect
on random variables.
And you can show that it reduces
the variance of your estimate
of the gradient.
So the question is,
is b really a constant
and seems to depend
on the trajectories?
We'll use the same value
of b for an entire batch,
for all of the examples.
And so we'll collect a batch of
data, then we will compute b,
and we'll then use b
for all of the updates
on that batch of data.
So how does it reduce the
variance of the gradient?
You can write down--
so this is the expectation
of the gradient.
You can write down the
variance analytically
and show that it
reduces the variance.
I don't want to go
through the math
because we have some other
stuff to get through.
But intuitively, you
can think about it
in terms of this example of--
it will encourage it to do
more of the above-average stuff
and less of the
below-average stuff.
I could also mention that
average reward is actually
not the optimal baseline.
You can actually
derive the variance,
and then take the derivative
of the variance side equal to 0
to find the optimal baseline.
But average reward
is pretty good.
The optimal baseline
is something--
it's very close
to average reward,
but there's some
additional weighting terms.
Cool.
So we have one more episode
of what does the gradient do.
And we're going to look
at a different example.
In this case, the robot
is folding a jacket.
And the reward is 1
if it's neatly folded,
0.5 if it's folded
with some wrinkles,
and 0 if it's not folded.
We're going to again
sample from our policy.
We have some samples of
not touching the jacket,
folding only the sleeves but
not folding the full thing,
flattening the jacket
but not folding it,
and one trajectory where
it does fold the jacket.
And my question is, with the
baseline in here this time,
what does the
gradient look like?
The rewards for 1, 2, and 3
will be 0, and the reward for 4
will be positive.
And so this means that
because of our baseline,
the gradient for
4 will be positive
and will encourage
this behavior.
And then we'll discourage all
the behavior for 1, 2, and 3.
Now, in some ways,
this is good because it
means that we are encouraging
the good behavior.
But there are also
some things that
are a little bit
dissatisfying about this.
The first is that the
gradient for 1, 2, and 3
is going to be identical
for all of them.
There isn't any
differentiation between them.
And some of these are
actually better than others.
And this is, in some ways, a
result of the reward function
that we're using, which is
more sparse than it could be.
And the other thing
is that we'll actually
see some techniques in Friday's
lecture that would actually
be able to leverage
some of the good parts
of these trajectories,
because there
is a good thing about
folding the sleeves,
and it would be nice to
be able to use that data
to encourage the policy.
And right now, it will
actually be discouraged
and have negative gradients
for this trajectory.
So in some ways, this is good.
So it will encourage
folding, but the gradient
is constant for
trajectories 1, 2, and 3.
And on Friday, we'll see ways to
make this a little bit better.
And one of the takeaways
here is that policy gradient
is still noisy and is
still high variance.
And it really is
going to work best
if you have dense rewards rather
than rewards that are sparse.
And it'll work best if you
have large batches of data,
because if you didn't actually
sample this fourth trajectory
and you only sampled failures,
then you would have 0 gradient.
And you wouldn't actually
be able to improve.
So the question was, can we just
improve the reward function?
Yes.
So if we had a more
dense reward function,
that would definitely
help in these cases.
There are actually scenarios
still where we could do better.
Especially if you, for
example, folded the sleeves,
you got positive
reward for this,
and then dropped it on
the ground or something
after that, then that's
still dissatisfying
because we wouldn't use the
first part successfully.
And we'll actually
see how to get
a good gradient for that first
part on Friday, but yeah.
If you had a more
dense reward function
for this particular
set of trajectories,
that would work a lot better.
Oh, so the question here
is, when we do the baseline,
are we also using this trick
to only use future rewards?
You can combine them.
You need to be a little bit--
you need to think a little
bit potentially more
carefully about what
the baseline will be,
because some of the rewards--
you'll be summing over
fewer things or more things,
depending on where you
are in the trajectory,
but you can definitely
combine them.
So the question was, if
we're using average reward
as the baseline, do we need
to keep updating the term?
Do we need to use
data from the policy?
So yes, you'll want
to keep on updating it
because as the policy
gets better, above average
and below average will change.
And you'll want to recompute it
on your latest batch of data.
Cool.
So one more thing on this
version of the algorithm,
and then we'll move on
to one last version,
in terms of how to
implement it, we
talked about-- we derived
the gradient like this.
And to actually implement
this in practice,
you could, in
principle, actually
just run a backward pass for
all of these different terms.
But if you computed all
of these individually,
then you'd have to do n
times t backward passes,
and this would be
rather inefficient.
And it'd be nice if we
could just actually do
automatic differentiation
on the full objective
and only do one forward
pass and one backward pass.
And we can do that.
So it's possible to
implement essentially
a surrogate objective
whose gradient
is the same as this objective.
I'm calling it surrogate
because it's not
the same as the very first
objective of maximizing expected
rewards.
But you can write down
a surrogate objective
for this particular example.
This is what the surrogate
objective looks like.
Note that I actually do have a
typo on these equations, where
this second sum should
be inside the first sum.
That's maybe a small note.
I'll see if I can fix that.
But, yeah, you can implement
a surrogate objective,
and then use backprop
and autodiff software
to just do one backward pass.
And what this actually
looks like in practice
is this would actually look
like a cross-entropy loss
for a discrete action policy,
or something like squared error
for our Gaussian policy.
You could also use more
sophisticated policies,
like diffusion or something
like that as well.
OK.
So summary so far, we
showed how to estimate
the gradient of the RL objective
using this log gradient trick.
This corresponds to weighing
the policy likelihood
by future rewards.
And we found that subtracting a
baseline, like average reward,
will also further
improve the gradient.
Even with these two things,
the gradient is still noisy,
and so it's best with large
batches and dense rewards.
This is also our first
online reinforcement
learning algorithm,
where we iterate
between collecting a batch
of data with our policy
and improve our policy.
And it formalizes this
trial-and-error learning
process.
And the intuition for
everything we've done so far
is do more of the
high-reward stuff
and less of the
low-reward stuff.
OK.
Now, the last thing
we'll talk about today
is what else is troublesome
about policy gradients?
And one thing that we haven't
really talked about that much
is the details of
the sampling process.
And this is what our gradient
and our algorithm looks like.
And note that in
this gradient, this
assumes that we're
sampling from pi-theta.
And we change theta in step 3.
And this means that every single
time we take a single gradient
step, we need to recollect
data to estimate our gradient.
And this is kind of
sad because usually we
do thousands and thousands
of gradient steps
on neural networks.
So yeah, that seems
like a problem.
And what this is called
is it's called on-policy.
It means that the gradient
that we are measuring
requires data using
our exact policy.
And we can think about--
this is an attribute of an
online RL algorithm, where
on-policy only uses data
from the current policy,
and off-policy means
that you can reuse data
from other past policies.
So can we derive an off-policy
version of the policy gradient?
And it's only going to
be a little off-policy.
And by that, I mean,
we're just going
to try to be able to take
more than one gradient
step on a single batch of data.
And to do this, we can
use importance sampling.
And importance sampling is
actually a really cool technique
that's useful outside of
reinforcement learning as well.
And it's thinking
about this scenario
where you want to estimate
a quantity, an expectation,
without actually sampling
from that distribution.
So say you have some expectation
using samples from p of x,
and you want to
estimate some function
f of x using those
samples, but say
that you only have access to the
ability to sample from q of x.
So this is usually called your
proposal distribution that's
able to propose samples to use.
This is your old policy.
We have samples
from our old policy,
but we want to be able to
estimate a function of samples
of our new policy after
we've taken a gradient step.
So what you can do in
this case if we write down
this expectation as an integral,
it looks something like this.
And as long as q of x
has reasonable support,
we can write this as--
we can add in this term that
equals 1 into our equation.
And then we can now actually
write this as an expectation
with respect to q.
So this is equal to an
expectation with respect
to q of p of x divided
by q of x times f of x.
And so this means that we
can actually estimate--
we can get this expectation
by sampling from q
and then weighting
the quantity by p/q.
[INAUDIBLE]
So that's pretty cool.
This means that we can
use principal samples
from our old policy
q, weight them
by the probability of the sample
under our new policy divided
by the probability under the
old policy times the quantity.
So we showed for
this simple case
of p of x and q of x in terms
of actually applying this
to our policy.
We can take our expected rewards
with regard to p of theta
if we instead have some
previous policy that we've
collected samples from.
We can then measure
our objective
in terms of the samples
from that policy, where
we weight the reward by the new
policy divided by the old policy
probability.
Now, note that this requires
your proposal distribution
to have nonzero
support in scenarios
where your new policy
has probability.
This is actually very important
for it to work if q of x is 0.
This is not poorly defined.
But that's really
the only catch here.
And in general, this
importance sampling technique
is really going to work
best when p and q--
or when your old policy
and your new policy--
are very similar to each other.
Now there's some details--
we've shown this in
terms of p of tau,
now how do we actually do this
in terms of pi of a given S?
That actually gets a
little bit trickier.
We can write down p
of tau and this ratio
as the product of these
different probabilities.
Unfortunately, some of the
probabilities cancel out.
But when we then try to
put these probabilities
into our update, we're
going to get something
like this, where we
then have this product
of these probability ratios.
And now, unfortunately,
this product
can actually become
very small or very large
if the length of your
trajectory is very large,
because you're going
to be multiplying
many, many numbers together.
If you have 100 numbers that
you're multiplying together,
if they're above 1, that
might start to get very large.
If they're below 1, that
might get to 0 very quickly.
And so in practice, we often
will consider the expectations
over time steps instead
of trajectories.
And that also has a little
bit of a hitch, which
is that this needs to be
over state action pairs
rather than actions
given states.
But often in practice,
we can approximate
this ratio as equal to 1.
This is incorrect, but it's
the best that we can do.
And then we can
get some final form
where we get this ratio of
new policy over old policy.
Cool.
The full algorithm
looks the same,
except now we can
take multiple gradient
steps on the same batch.
This is good.
And then we have this new
form for our gradient.
OK.
We'll talk a little
bit about some tricks.
We don't have time to
cover KL constraints today,
but to review things, we
talked about online RL.
It's an on-policy algorithm.
We talked about baselines
for reducing variance.
And we also just derived this
off-policy policy gradient,
which uses importance
sampling and allows
us to apply multiple
gradient steps.
The intuition is to do more
high-reward stuff and less
low-reward stuff.
And the gradient is
still very noisy and best
with large batches
and dense rewards.
Cool.
And that's it for today.
Next time, we'll talk about
actor-critic methods, which
we'll build closely on
what we talked about today,
including PPO.